window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Computer_Organization - Secondary_Storage — Slot 1 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Secondary_Storage — Slot 1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Consider a disk with the following specifications: rotation speed of 6000 RPM,\naverage seek time of 5 milliseconds, 500 sectors/track, 512-byte sectors.\nA file has content stored in 3000 sectors located randomly on the disk. Assuming\naverage rotational latency, the total time (in seconds, rounded off to 2 decimal\nplaces) to read the entire file from the disk is _______ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "29.5",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422854/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-43#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Consider a 512 GB hard disk with 32 storage surfaces. There are 4096 sectors per\ntrack and each sector holds 1024 bytes of data. The number of cylinders in the hard\ndisk is ____ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "4096",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422798/gate-cse-2024-set-1-question-44#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>A magnetic disk has 100 cylinders, each with 10 tracks of 10 sectors. If each sector contains 128 bytes, what is the maximum capacity of the disk in kilobytes? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>12,80,000</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1280</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1250</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1,28,000</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>1250</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/331420/isro2020-46\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>A particular disk unit uses a bit string to record the occupancy or vacancy of its tracks, with 0 denoting vacant and 1 for occupied. A 32-bit segment of this string has hexadecimal value D4FE2003. The percentage of occupied tracks for the corresponding part of the disk, to the nearest percentage is: <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>12</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>25</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>38</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>44</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>44</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213538/isro2018-50\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>SATA is the abbreviation of <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2017)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Serial Advanced Technology Attachment</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Serial Advanced Technology Architecture</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Serial Advanced Technology Adapter</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Serial Advanced Technology Array</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Serial Advanced Technology Attachment</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/128688/isro2017-46\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Consider a disk pack with 16 surfaces, 128 tracks per surface and 256 sectors per track. 512 bytes of data are stored in a bit serial manner in a sector. The capacity of the disk pack and the number of bits required to specify a particular sector in the disk are respectively: <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2016)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>256  Mbyte, 19 bits</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>256 Mbyte, 28 bits</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>512 Mbyte, 20 bits</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>64 Gbyte, 28 bits</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>256  Mbyte, 19 bits</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1209/gate2007-11-isro2009-36-isro2016-21\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>A hard disk system has the following parameters :<br>Number of tracks =500<br>Number of sectors/track =100<br>Number of bytes /sector =500<br>Time taken by the head to move from one track to adjacent track =1 ms<br>Rotation speed =600 rpm.<br>What is the average time taken for transferring 250 bytes from the disk ? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>300.5 ms</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>255.5 ms</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>255 ms</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>300 ms</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>300 ms</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3479/gate2007-it-44-isro2015-34\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Six files F1, F2, F3, F4, F5 and F6 have 100, 200, 50, 80, 120, 150 records respectively. In what order should they be stored so as to optimize act. Assume each file is accessed with the same frequency <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>F3, F4, F1, F5, F6, F2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>F2, F6, F5, F1, F4, F3</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>F1, F2, F3, F4, F5, F6</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Ordering is immaterial as all files are accessed with the same frequency.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>F3, F4, F1, F5, F6, F2</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/37207/isro2015-13\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Consider a typical disk that rotates at 15000 rotations per minute (RPM) and has a transfer rate of 50x\\(10^{6}\\)  bytes/sec. If the average seek time of the disk is twice the average rotational delay and the controller's transfer time is 10 times the disk transfer time, the average time (in milliseconds) to read or write a 512-byte sector of the disk is ______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "6.1",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8251/gate2015-2-32#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Consider a disk pack with a seek time of 4 milliseconds and rotational speed of 10000 rotations per minute (RPM). It has 600 sectors per track and each sector can store 512 bytes of data. Consider a file stored in the disk. The file contains 2000 sectors. Assume that every sector access necessitates a seek, and the average rotational latency for accessing each sector is half of the time for one complete rotation. The total time (in milliseconds) needed to read the entire file is ____________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "14020",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8354/gate2015-1-44#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>In case of a DVD, the speed of data transfer is mentioned in multiples of? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>150 KB/s</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1.38 MB/s</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>300 KB/s</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2.40 MB/s</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>1.38 MB/s</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/44397/isro-2013-51\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Consider a hard disk with 16 recording surfaces (0-15) having 16384 cylinders (0-16383) and each\ncylinder contains 64 sectors (0-63). Data storage capacity in each sector is 512 bytes. Data are\norganized cylinder-wise and the addressing format is (cylinder no., surface no., sector no.). A file\nof size 42797 KB is stored in the disk and the starting disk location of the file is (1200, 9, 40).\nWhat is the cylinder number of the last sector of the file, if it is stored in a contiguous manner? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1281</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1282</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1283</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1284</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>1284</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1540/gate2013-29#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Which RAID level gives block level striping with double distributed parity? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>RAID 10</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>RAID 2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>RAID 6</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>RAID 5</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>RAID 6</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/52586/isro2011-46\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>A fast wide SCSI-II disk drive spins at 7200 RPM, has a sector size of 512 bytes, and holds 160 sectors per track. Estimate the sustained transfer rate of this drive <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>576000 Kilobytes / sec</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>9600 Kilobytes / sec</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>4800 Kilobytes / sec</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>19200 Kilobytes / sec</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>9600 Kilobytes / sec</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/52486/isro2011-38\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>An application loads 100 libraries at startup. Loading each library requires exactly\none disk access. The seek time of the disk to a random location is given as 10ms.\nRotational speed of disk is 6000rpm. If all 100 libraries are loaded from random\nlocations on the disk, how long does it take to load all libraries? (The time to\ntransfer data from the disk block once the head has been positioned at the start\nof the block may be neglected) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0.5s</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1.5s</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1.25s</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1s</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>1.5s</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2146/gate2011-44#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
